Guide to the Henry Walter Papers 1950-2017 MS 3016
New-York Historical Society
Henry Walter papers
1950-2017
New-York Historical Society
Walter, Henry, 1927-2016
MS 3016
40.67 Linear feet in 35 record cartons, 8 document boxes and 1 oversize folder
The Henry Walter papers primarily include Walter's files as a speechwriter for New York City Comptroller (1970-1973) and Mayor (1974-1977) Abraham D. Beame. The files include drafts and final versions of speeches, messages to constituent groups, press releases, correspondence and memos, Beame's daily public schedules, event invitations and related background briefing notes, and other documents concerning public relations activities in Beame's office. The papers also include files related to Walter's work as Press Secretary for Robert Morgenthau's 1962 campaign for New York State governor and as the first Director of Public Information for the newly-formed New York City Department of Highways in 1963-1964. The papers also hold a broad range of New York City-oriented print matter, such as city government reports and local newsletters. Among these is a rich set of programs, seating charts and other documents ranging from 1956 to 2017 from the annual political parody show presented by the Inner Circle, an organization of New York City journalists and reporters.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in five series:
Series I. Public Relations Files. Abraham D. Beame (1961-2000s, bulk 1969-1977)
Series II. Public Relations Files. Harrison J. Goldin (1976-1990s, bulk 1978-1989)
Series III. Public Relations Files. Other (1951-1993, bulk 1960s)
Series IV. Inner Circle Show (1956-2014)
Series V. Print Matter (1950-2001)
Biographical/Historical Note
Henry (Hank) Walter (1927-2016) joined New York City Comptroller Abraham D. Beame's staff in September 1970 as Assistant to the Comptroller for Public Relations. In this capacity he wrote speeches for Beame, as well as press releases and messages to groups, and handled select correspondence on public relations matters.
After attending St. Joseph's College and Fordham University, and a stint in the Army, Walter's professional career began in 1953 as a copy boy with the New York World-Telegram. He became a reporter for the newspaper, first on civil service issues, then covering City Hall. He left the World-Telegram in August 1962 to become Press Secretary for gubernatorial candidate Robert Morgenthau. In January 1963, Walter became the first Director of Public Information for the newly-formed New York City Department of Highways. He left the Department in March 1964, joining WMCA Radio as Director of Editorial Research, and was later promoted to Director of Public Affairs for Straus Broadcasting Group, of which WMCA was a part.
Walter left WMCA in mid-1970 and was hired on to Beame's staff by his Executive Assistant, Dominick R. Peluso, who was a former reporter himself and knew Walter from their years on the City Hall beat for rival papers. Peluso left Beame's staff in January 1972 for a job with the Queens Public Administrator, and he was replaced by Ed Katcher, another former reporter. In November 1973, Beame won New York's mayoral election, and Walter stayed on as a speechwriter for Mayor Beame with the title of Special Assistant to the Mayor. In this position, Walter reported to Press Secretary Sidney J. Frigand and worked with other speechwriters and public relations staff, including the future Lincoln scholar, Harold Holzer.
Abraham D. Beame (1906-2001) was a graduate of the City College of New York and a Certified Public Accountant who began working for the city's budget bureau in 1946. Beame was first elected Comptroller in 1962. He left the office in 1965 to run for mayor on the Democratic Party ticket. He lost that election to John V. Lindsay, but returned to public service four years later in January 1970 upon his re-election as Comptroller. In the next election cycle, Beame again ran for mayor, winning this time. He was inaugurated on January 1, 1974. Although his mayoralty had moments of celebration, such as the events surrounding the 1976 Bicentennial of the United States' Declaration of Independence, Beame's tenure was marked more by fiscal crises (including the threat of bankruptcy), crime (including the Son of Sam serial murders), the failure to deliver basic services (including the power black-out of 1977), and other troubles. Beame ran for re-election in the mayoral campaign of 1977, but lost in the Democratic Party primary.
As Beame's days in office came to a close, Walter transferred in November 1977 to work as a speechwriter for Comptroller Harrison J. Goldin, a position he held until 1989 when Goldin left the Comptrollership after a failed effort to win that year's mayoral election.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The collection was donated by Henry Walter's son, Paul A. Walter, in November 2015.
Scope and Contents Note
The Henry Walter papers primarily include Walter's working files from his years as an assistant for public relations matters, especially in connection with speechwriting, for New York City Comptroller (1970-1973) and Mayor (1974-1977) Abraham (Abe) D. Beame. The files include press releases, drafts and final versions of speeches/remarks, mayoral messages/greetings to constituent and other groups, daily press schedules, briefing memos on appearances (e.g., other attendees, important background information, logistics), invitations for Beame to attend events and programs or other documents related to those events, internal memos, city government agency reports, and other materials related to Beame's public appearances and communications. The collection also holds the public relations work Walter did for Robert Morgenthau during his campaign for New York Governor in 1962, the press releases Walter prepared for the newly-formed Department on Highways in 1963-1964, and other work Walter did in the 1990s.
The collection holds a rich set of documents related to the Inner Circle annual political parody show. These include programs for all years from 1956 to 1999 and many from 2001-2017, along with seating charts, invitations, tickets, and other documents. Finally, the collection holds an idiosyncratic mix of newsletters, newspapers, commemorative booklets, and other print material on economic, political and cultural matters from the 1950s to 2001.
The collection also holds Walter's files from his work from November 1977 to 1989 for Comptroller Harrison J. Goldin.
Controllership -- New York (State) -- New York -- Public relations.; Mayors -- New York (State) -- New York -- Public relations.; Letters (correspondence); Memorandums.; Newsletters.; Press releases.; Souvenir programs.; Speeches (documents); Inner Circle of New York Political Journalists; Beame, Abraham D. (Abraham David), 1906-2001; Goldin, Harrison J.
- Series I. Public Relations Files. Abraham D. Beame, 1961-2000s (bulk, 1969-1977); 22.92 Linear feet
  Arrangement Note
  The series is organized in two subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Comptrollership Years 1961-1974 (bulk, 1969-1973)
  Subseries II.B. Mayoralty Years 1960s-2000s (bulk, 1974-1977)
  Scope and Contents Note
  The series includes Henry Walter's files from his years as an assistant for public relations matters, especially in connection with speechwriting, for Comptroller (1970-1973) and Mayor (1974-1977) Abraham (Abe) D. Beame. The series generally includes three types of content: press releases from Beame's office and other public statements made by Beame; working files underlying Walter's public relations activities; and newspaper clippings. The working files include drafts and final versions of speeches/remarks, messages/greetings, daily press schedules, press releases, proclamations, briefing memos on appearances (e.g., other attendees, important background information, logistics), invitations for Beame to attend events and programs or other documents related to those events, internal memos, Walter's timesheets and daily to-do lists, city government agency reports, and other materials related to Beame's public appearances and communications. The subject matter primarily concerns city finances, politics, crime, drug abuse, and other such broad issues facing Beame, but also concerns specific events such as the celebration of the nation's bicentennial in 1976 and the power outage/black-out of 1977.
  The series also includes some documents, including original correspondence, from the 1960s primarily related to Beame's positions on tax and revenue public policy matters, and some material from Beame's post-mayoralty years.
  - Subseries I.A. Comptrollership Years, 1961-1974 (bulk, 1969-1973); 8.75 Linear feet
    The subseries primarily includes Henry Walter's files from his years as Assistant to the Comptroller for Public Relations, from September 1970 to the end of Abraham (Abe) Beame's tenure as Comptroller at December 31, 1973. The subseries generally includes three types of content: press releases from Beame's office and other public statements made by Beame; working files underlying Walter's public relations activities; and newspaper clippings. The subseries also includes some documents, including original correspondence, from the 1960s primarily related to Beame's positions on tax and revenue public policy matters; these pre-date Walter's involvement with Beame and likely were given to Walter in connection with his public relations responsibilities.
    Press releases are found as four bound annual volumes for 1970-1973 and as unbound, foldered documents for the same years. The two sets appear to be largely identical. One important known exception is that the unbound documents include the press releases issued separately during Beame's 1973 mayoral campaign and the transition period after his election. In addition to press releases, these documents include other forms of public relations material, such as speeches, remarks, messages, and the like. The sets each have "indexes," which include a table of contents indicating date and subject matter of the documents. The bulk of the topics concern financial matters, such as bond sales, budgets, New York City's credit rating, governmental unit reorganizations and appointments, mass transit fares, expenses (e.g., Board of Education deficits, process for awarding management consultant contracts), and housing construction. Many of the topics, though financial in emphasis, have broader implications as well, such as drug addiction/drug abuse, the city's costs related to United Nations operations, home rule legislation in the state, proposed Manhattan House of Detention (Tombs) prison annex, and the Yankee Stadium renovation. There are also topics concerning national legislation (e.g., wage and price controls) and international matters, especially with respect to Israel (e.g., support for Soviet Jews, call for a UN investigation into Arab guerilla sabotage against people flying in and out of Israel, providing military jet planes to Israel, remarks at memorial services for the slain Israeli Olympic team members).
    Working files include a mix of documents, including drafts of speeches and press releases (including unused material), Beame's daily public schedules, carbon copies of outgoing correspondence over Beame's or Walter's signature, Walter's to-do lists, notes, and time records, clippings, and reports issued by the Comptroller's Office and other print matter, including the employee newsletter The Comptroller. One file includes the development of Beame's mayoral candidacy announcement, with Walter's observations on the events of that time (March 1973). Threaded throughout the files are glimpses of Walter himself, including carbon copies of short letters to his mother or to friends and professional colleagues. Most of these files are structured chronologically, with all matters from a given period of time (typically one month) filed together. A few files are subject-oriented and include correspondence, press releases, and other documents related to particular topics. These include a compendium of mayoral candidate Beame's campaign promises and documents related to the efforts of one Abraham Broza to collect signatures on petitions in support of certain of Beame's positions. These files also include Beame's correspondence with state and city officials from the late 1960s, that is, prior to his comptrollership, concerning his positions on tax and revenue reform measures.
    The files of clippings include mostly photocopies of articles from the New York Times, Daily News, Post, and other newspapers that concern Beame and New York City issues of interest to Walter as Beame's public relations assistant. The files are especially extensive for 1973 and include the coverage of Beame's mayoralty campaign.
    The subseries is arranged with the press releases first, followed by the work files, subject files, and clippings files.
    Separated Materials Note
    Some print matter was removed from the collection to be cataloged and shelved individually in the Library collection. The catalog entries refer to the fact that they were originally part of the Henry Walter collection. Many of these removed reports were duplicates of those in the collection; among those removed without duplicates remaining were the Comptroller's Annual Reports for 1971-72 and 1972-73; the New York State Statistical Yearbook for 1972; the New York City Statistical Guide for 1964; and Comptroller's reports on the Phoenix House program (1970), middle-income housing program (1971), and Health and Hospitals Corporation (1971).
    - Press Releases, 1970. #1-175 (Bound) (Offsite-box 1, Volume 1)
    - Press Releases, 1971. #1-190 (Bound) (Offsite-box 1, Volume 2)
    - Press Releases, 1972. #1-257 (Bound) (Offsite-box 2, Volume 1)
    - Press Releases, 1973. #1-319 (Bound) (Offsite-box 3, Volume 1)
    - Press Releases, 1970. Indexes (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    - Press Releases, 1970. #1-175 (5 folders) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2-6)
    - Press Releases, 1971. Indexes (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases, 1971. #1-190 (5 folders) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8-12)
    - Press Releases, 1972. Indexes (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
    - Press Releases, 1972. #1-257 (7 folders) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14-20)
    - Press Releases, 1973. Indexes (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    - Press Releases, 1973. #1-310 (9 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2-10)
    - Press Releases, Mayoral Campaign, 1973. Indexes (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
    - Press Releases, Mayoral Campaign, 1973. #1-216 (5 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12-16)
    - Working Files. 1970 May-August (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
    - Working Files. 1970 September (2 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18-19)
    - Working Files. 1970 October (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20)
    - Working Files. 1970 November (Offsite-box 5, Folder 21)
    - Working Files. 1970 November?-December (Offsite-box 5, Folder 22)
      Includes a copy of the report prepared by the Comptroller's Office School Construction Costs: A Study in Escalation.
    - Working Files. 1971 January (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
    - Working Files. 1971 February (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2-3)
      Includes the Comptroller's Office report concerning the condition of the Tax Deficiency Account and the Tax Appropriation and General Fund Stabilization Reserve Fund ("Rainy Day Account") for 1971-72 and the report concerning the proposed Executive Capital Budget for 1971-72.
    - Working Files. 1971 March (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
      Includes the Comptroller's reports Investment Progress concerning the New York City Retirement Systems as of 30 June 1970 and the Special Survey of the Board of Education's Projected Operating Deficit, and the handbooks for New York City managerial employees describing their welfare fund benefits (1969, 1971).
    - Working Files. 1971 March-April (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
    - Working Files. 1971 May (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
      Includes a copy of the booklet New York City Does Have a Future by Eli Ginzberg.
    - Working Files. 1971 June (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
    - Working Files. 1971 July (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
    - Working Files. 1971 July-August (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
      Includes the Comptroller's Office report Declining Attendance in New York City's School System.
    - Working Files. 1971 August (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10-11)
      Includes the Summer issue of the Kingsbrook Auxiliary Reporter with photographs from the 16 May 1971 Dinner-Dance at which Comptroller Beame was honored. Includes the Comptroller's Office interim and second interim reports on the Municipal Loan Program.
    - Working Files. 1971 September (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12-13)
      Includes to-do lists that range from August to December.
    - Working Files. 1971 September-October (Offsite-box 6, Folder 14)
    - Working Files. 1971 October (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 15-16)
      Includes the Comptroller's report concerning the 1972-73 draft capital budget and the capital program for the five succeeding fiscal years.
    - Working Files. 1971 November (Offsite-box 6, Folder 17)
      Includes the Comptroller's preliminary report concerning the Department of Social Services' Day Care Imprest (Revolving) Fund.
    - Working Files. 1971 December (Offsite-box 6, Folder 18)
    - Working Files. 1972 January (Offsite-box 6, Folder 19)
    - Working Files. 1972 February (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 20-21)
      Includes the Comptroller's reports concerning the Department of Rent and Housing Maintenance's Emergency Services Repair Program, the 1972-74 Executive Capital Budget, the 1972-73 proposed expense budget, and The Case for Upgrading New York City's Credit Rating.
    - Working Files. 1972 March (Offsite-box 6, Folder 22)
      Includes the Comptroller's report Investment Progress concerning the New York City Retirement Systems as of 30 June 1971.
    - Working Files. 1972 April (Offsite-box 6, Folder 23)
    - Working Files. 1972 May (Offsite-box 6, Folder 24)
    - Working Files. 1972 June (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
      Includes the Comptroller's report on the Office of Neighborhood Government's Neighborhood Action Program.
    - Working Files. 1972 July (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
      Includes the Comptroller's report "The Forgotten Children": A Second Study of School Truancy.
    - Working Files. 1972 August (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
      Includes the Comptroller's report of the limited survey of the Parking Violations Bureau for compliance with the Marchi Bill (Scofflaw Law).
    - Working Files. 1972 September (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    - Working Files. 1972 October (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
      Includes the Comptroller's report concerning the 1973-74 draft capital budget and the capital program for the five succeeding fiscal years.
    - Working Files. 1972 October-November (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
      Includes the Comptroller's reports on the John Edward Bruce Day Care Center Number One and the Youth Board Research Institute of New York Inc.'s High School and Educational Incentive Program ("other than personal services" only).
    - Working Files. 1972 December (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
      Includes the Comptroller's report concerning the Youth Services Agency and City and State Funded Contracts with the Youth Board Institute of New York, Inc.
    - Working Files. 1973 January (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
      Includes the Comptroller's reports on New York City Off-Track Betting (OTB) Corporation and Investment Progress concerning the New York City Retirement Systems as of 30 June 1972.
    - Working Files. 1973 February (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
      Includes the Comptroller's Office report concerning the condition of the Tax Deficiency Account and the Tax Appropriation and General Fund Stabilization Reserve Fund ("Rainy Day Account") in the proposed 1973-74 expense budget. Also includes a report prepared for the Comptroller on the South Bronx Model Cities Camping Program's activities at Shaker Village Work Group Camp in Pittsfield, Massachusetts.
    - Working Files. 1973 March (3 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10-12)
    - Working Files. 1973 March. Mayoral Candidacy Announcement, 1965, 1973 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
      Includes drafts of the announcement, Walter's notes on discussions planning the announcement (March 8) and other public relations matters for the campaign in March, Jimmy Breslin's age-related criticism of Beame's candidacy and drafts of the response, campaign handbills and pamphlets, and other matters from the first weeks of Beame's candidacy. Includes a transcript of NBC's Meet the Press broadcast of October 17, 1965, which included mayoral candidates Beame, William F. Buckley, Jr. and John V. Lindsay.
    - Working Files. 1973 April (2 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14-15)
    - Working Files. 1973 May (Offsite-box 7, Folder 16)
    - Working Files. 1973 June (Offsite-box 7, Folder 17)
    - Working Files. 1973 July (Offsite-box 7, Folder 18)
    - Working Files. 1973 August (Offsite-box 7, Folder 19)
    - Working Files. 1973 September (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
    - Working Files. 1973 October (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
      Includes the October 1973 issue of the periodical The Young Democrat focusing on the upcoming election and the program for the New York Press Club's 25th Anniversary Byline Ball at the Hotel Roosevelt. Includes the Comptroller's report concerning the 1974-75 draft capital budget and the capital program for the five succeeding fiscal years.
    - Working Files. 1973 November (3 folders) (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3-5)
      Includes an invitation to the Beame pre-election rally on November 4 and two photographs of Beame and his wife, likely at the election night celebration. Includes copies of "Managing New York City's Pension Funds," an undated presentation to the Legislature's Select Committee on Pensions by Third Deputy Comptroller Melvin N. Lechner.
    - Working Files. 1973 December (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
      Includes the Comptroller's report Investment Progress concerning the New York City Retirement Systems as of 30 June 1973.
    - Press Releases. Credit Ratings, 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
    - Credit Rating Hearing Transcript, Circa 1972 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 8)
      Includes pages 74-132 of a transcript of a Congressional hearing concerning bond ratings.
    - Abraham Broza Petitions, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
      Includes correspondence and other documents related to Broza's efforts to garner public support for Beame's positions, primarily on the city's credit rating (1972) and the CUNY budget and the 35 cent transit fare (1973).
    - Street Crime / Juvenile Delinquency, 1973 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10)
      Includes letters from Lou Shainmark, former Managing Editor of the Chicago Herald American, with proposals for reducing New York youth street crime.
    - Youth Services Agency Expenses, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 11)
      Includes press releases, clippings and other documents concerning inquiries into the YSA's expenses.
    - Press Releases. State-City Fiscal Commission, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 12)
      Includes two releases, 70-22 and 71-107.
    - CUNY Faculty Appointment, 1973 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 13)
      Includes correspondence concerning a dispute over a job offer of a professorship.
    - Reconciliations of City Accounts, 1972 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 14)
    - Compendium of Beame's Campaign Proposals, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15)